<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ThreatDetection on lolcads tech blog</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/tags/threatdetection/</link><description>Recent content in ThreatDetection on lolcads tech blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>lolcads@posteo.net (lolcads)</managingEditor><webMaster>lolcads@posteo.net (lolcads)</webMaster><copyright>lolcads</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 10:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lolcads.github.io/tags/threatdetection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Outsmarting the Watchdog: How can Adversaries evade Sigma Rule Detection during a Kerberos Golden Ticket Attack?</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2025/01/evadingsigma/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>lolcads@posteo.net (lolcads)</author><guid>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2025/01/evadingsigma/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of increasing amounts of cyber threats, organizations employ security information and event management (SIEM) systems as a way to collect and analyze information at a central place to detect and counteract against potential cyberattacks.
One common way to detect malicious behavior using this information are &lt;a href="https://sigmahq.io/docs/basics/rules.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Sigma rules&lt;/a&gt;
 and the corresponding Sigma detection format.
Given that these rules are open source, attackers can check if their behavior is detected by them and might try to obfuscate their attacks to evade detection, e.g., by adapting used commands.
Thus, it is important that these rules are robust to changes of the detected behavior - both malicious but also accidental.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>*PowerView* is evil, but *PowerVi* and *ew* are legit, right? - Missing signature-based detections due to PowerShell Script Block Logging Fragmentation</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2024/04/psscriptblockfragmentation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 11:01:40 +0200</pubDate><author>lolcads@posteo.net (lolcads)</author><guid>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2024/04/psscriptblockfragmentation/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="powerview-is-evil-but-powervi-and-ew-are-legit-right---missing-signature-based-detections-due-to-powershell-script-block-logging-fragmentation"&gt;&lt;em&gt;PowerView&lt;/em&gt; is evil, but &lt;em&gt;PowerVi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ew&lt;/em&gt; are legit, right? - Missing signature-based detections due to PowerShell Script Block Logging Fragmentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="update-15082024"&gt;Update [15/08/2024]:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="https://x.com/nas_bench/status/1806253324456403316" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;short discussion on X&lt;/a&gt;
 the source code of the PowerShell Script Block Fragmentation was &lt;a href="https://github.com/PowerShell/PowerShell/blob/7ec8e4ed8f47e81e70de5353500f8a01d5fe396c/src/System.Management.Automation/engine/runtime/CompiledScriptBlock.cs#L1451-L1454" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;linked&lt;/a&gt;
.
Looking at the comment in the code, it becomes clear that the size of a script block fragment is intentionally set to a random value in order to deny attackers the easy possibility to split their scripts as they wish.
If a script block is larger than 20000 (Unicode) characters, it is split into fragments with sizes 10000 plus a random value between 0 and 10000 - resulting in script block sizes from 10000 to 20000 characters.
Further research is needed to answer the question if and how the fragmentation of PowerShell script blocks can still be exploited.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>