<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Network on lolcads tech blog</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/tags/network/</link><description>Recent content in Network on lolcads tech blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>user@example.com (Hugo Author)</managingEditor><webMaster>user@example.com (Hugo Author)</webMaster><copyright>lolcads</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 13:09:24 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lolcads.github.io/tags/network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>friTap - Decrypting TLS on the fly</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2022/08/fritap/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 13:09:24 +0200</pubDate><author>user@example.com (Hugo Author)</author><guid>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2022/08/fritap/</guid><description>Encryption - a curse and a blessing at the same time Digital communication in today&amp;rsquo;s world has a particularly high status in our society. Financial transactions are conducted via online banking, private communication is increasingly limited to digital messenger services, and even health data is experiencing a shift to digital form. Due to the growth of such sensitive digital data, the need for secure transmission of such data has become increasingly important over the past decades.</description></item><item><title>libdesock</title><link>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2022/02/libdesock/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 14:24:40 +0100</pubDate><author>user@example.com (Hugo Author)</author><guid>https://lolcads.github.io/posts/2022/02/libdesock/</guid><description>Fuzzing Network Applications with AFL and libdesock Fuzzing network servers with AFL is challenging since AFL provides its input via stdin or command line arguments while servers get their input over network connections. As the popularity of AFL grew, many attempts have been made of fuzzing popular servers like apache and nginx using different techniques and hacky workarounds. However an off-the-shelf network fuzzing solution for AFL didn&amp;rsquo;t exist for a long time until so-called &amp;ldquo;desocketing&amp;rdquo; tools emerged.</description></item></channel></rss>